Register of the Kurt Robert Mattusch Papers, 1919-1969.
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS. See also SUBJECT FILE -- Korea -- Agencies -- Economic Research Center
  - "The U.S.A." Fortune, February 1940
    - Typewritten notes (Folder 37)
  - "The Breadline," 29 July 1940. Typescript (Folder 38)
  - "British Policy in India," 1941 (Box 9.)
    - Correspondence (Folder 1)
    - Introduction, Preface, Table of Contents (Folder 2)
    - Part I, "Stages of Constitutional Reform." Typescript (Folder 3-4)
    - Part II, "Conventions of Administration." Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "India," 6 November 1941. Correspondence, memoranda, outline (Folder 6)
  - "The Lonely Wayfarer," short story, Esquire, December 1941. Printed copy (Folder 7)
  - "Move Industry to the Battlefront," December 1941. Correspondence, outline (Folder 8)
  - "Two Schisms = Three Indias," 1942? Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "India: Ally or Enemy?" Decision, January- February 1942. Correspondence, printed copy, review of the article, typescript (Folder 10)
  - "India: Pivot of Allied Offensive," 6 January 1942. Outline (Folder 11)
  - "Enter, India," 14 January 1942. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Strategical India," 16 January 1942. Correspon- dence, outline, typescript (Folder 13)
  - "Politics in India," 18 January 1942. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Stalemate in India," 20 January 1942. Correspon- dence, typescript (Folder 15)
  - "India as a War Arsenal," 9 February 1942. Typescript, typewritten notes (Folder 16)
  - "India's Rendezvous with Destiny," 16 March 1942. Outline (Folder 17)
  - "India's Secret Independence," 18 March 1942. Outline (Folder 18)
  - "Heartland in Reverse," 28 March 1942. Handwritten notes, outline (Folder 19)
  - "India's Basic Problem (Rich India, Poor India)," 1 April 1942. Outline (Folder 20)
  - "India's Economic Emancipation," 2 April 1942. Outline (Folder 21)
  - "Memo to the India Mission," 2 April 1942. Outline (Folder 22)
  - "Turning the Tables on Haushofer," 6 April 1942. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - "Discovering India," 16 April 1942. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - "Another Four Hundred Million Customers (Industrial Revolution Comes to India)," 27 April 1942. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - "The Metamorphosis of Asia," 11 May 1942. Typescript (Folder 26)
  - "Why the Indians Don't Fight," Common Sense, June 1942. Printed copy, review, typescript (Folder 27)
  - "Geopolitics, Science of Power Politics," Amerasia, July 1942. Correspondence, handwritten notes, outline, typescript (Folder 28)
  - "Appointment With My Government," 5 July 1942. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - "Paradox in India," 16 August 1942. Typescript (Folder 30)
  - "The American Public and India," 23 September 1942. Typescript Typescript (Folder 31)
  - "Necessity Begets World Economy," 30 November 1942. (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - "Beyond Geo-Political Myths," review of J. F. Horrabin, An Outline of Political Geography, The New Leader, 23 January 1943. Correspondence. printed copy, typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Preliminary Recommendation on Postwar Problems of the Inter-American Juridical Committee," International Conciliation, February 1943. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Britain without India," Amerasia, 25 April 1943. Printed copy and typescript (Folder 4)
  - "A Profile of India," 26 April 1942. Correspondence, typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Global Front -- Dreamers and Schemers," Common Sense, May 1943. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Britain and India," 16 May 1943. Handwritten and typewritten notes, map, memorandum, typescript (Folder 7)
  - "A Man and a City, A Case Study of New York Politics, 1900-1940," November 1944. Chapters are in typescript unless otherwise noted
    - General. Clippings, contracts, handwritten and typewritten notes, speeches of Raymond V. Ingersoll (Folder 8)
    - Correspondence
      - 1933-1941 (Folder 9)
      - 1942-1945 (Folder 10)
    - Outline, table of contents (Folder 11)
    - "A Youth Finds His Place in the World" (Folder 12)
    - "Politicians, Reformers, and Political Servants" (Folder 13)
    - "The City and the State" (Folder 14)
    - "The Face of the City Changes" (Folder 15)
    - "Capital and Labor Sit Together" (Box 11., Folder 1)
    - "The City Government Matures" (Folder 2)
    - "One Man's Strength." Handwritten and typewritten notes, typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Gross National Product of Germany, 1936-1944," 1945? Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "The Art of Compromise," 1947? Holograph (Folder 5)
  - "Analysis of Existing Governmental Structures in the Four Zones of Occupation," 30 January 1947. Handwritten notes, typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Die Moeglichkeit der Verbesserung der Lebens- standards in Deutschland und die Wiederein- gliederung der Deutschen Wirtschaft in den groesseren Rahmen der europaeischen und der Weltwirtschaft," speech, 3 December 1947. Handwritten notes, poster, summary, typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Zur Deutschen Einheit," radio broadcast, 1948. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Untitled writing on Austrian balance of payment, 1949. Typewritten notes (Folder 9)
  - "The Tones," short story, 1950. Correspondence, typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Dynamics in Indian Development," speech, 25 March 1955. Outline, request to deliver the speech (Folder 11)
  - Untitled speech on Indian economic conditions, 30 March 1955. Handwritten notes, holograph (Folder 12)
  - "Economic Problems in India," speech, 2 May 1955. Outline, request to deliver the speech (Folder 13)
  - "Tradition and Change in India," 15 September. Outline, request to deliver the speech (Folder 14)
  - "What Price Tourism?" Korea Times, 4 October 1962. Printed copy (Folder 15)
  - Letter to the editor, Korea Times?, 7 March 1962. Printed copy (Folder 16)
  - Letter to the editor, Korea Times?, 13 June 1962? Printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "Korean Economics and Rural Handicraft" (in Korean), Rural Economics, 12, 1962 (Folder 18)
  - "Problems in Korean Economics" (in Korean), Business, March 1963 (Folder 19)
  - "Ramie, 'Miracle Plant,' Hidden Natural Wealth," Korean Republic, 12 May 1963. Printed copy (Folder 20)
  - "Foreigners Not Wanted?" Korea Times, 21 May 1963. Printed copy (Folder 21)
  - "How to Make Development Pay!" Korea Times, 6 June 1963. Printed copy (Folder 22)
  - "In a Time of Indecision," Korea Times, 27 June 1963. Printed copy (Folder 23)
- LECTURES AND NOTES
  - General (Box 11., Folder 24)
  - European Economy after World War II (Folder 25)
  - Germany
    - Acquaintances of Kurt R. Mattusch in 1930s -- Profiles (Folder 26)
    - Development of Political Parties, 1932 (Folder 27)
    - Place in Europe after World War II (Folder 28)
    - Under Hitler's Rule (Folder 29-30)
    - Unemployed in 1932 (Folder 31)
  - History of Western Civilization from Ancient Egypt through Industrial Revolution (Box 12., Folder 1-6)
  - India -- Economic and Social Problems (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - "Natural Laws" (Folder 2)
  - United States -- Social Problems, 1939 (Folder 3)
- SUBJECT FILE
  - Dictatorship of the Proletariat (Box 13., Folder 4)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation (Folder 5)
  - Geopolitics (Folder 6)
  - Germany
    - General
      - Kurka, Walter, "Troestung im Walde," short story, n.d. Mimeograph (Folder 7)
      - Labor and Laboring Classes, 1918-1944. Manual of the United States government, 1944. Mimeograph (Folder 8)
      - Mattusch -- Genealogy, 1819-1937 (Folder 9)
      - "Die Naechte der Jugend," poem, n.d. Typed copy (Folder 10)
      - Peterichs -- History of a Family. Correspondence, 1924-1948 (Folder 11)
    - 1919-1932
      - Bacmeister, Ernst, "Der Mensch des guten Willen," religious treatise, 1932. Printed copy (Folder 12)
      - Bavaria -- Law on Chamber of Commerce and Industries, 1927 (Folder 13)
      - Broadcasting -- Law, 1932 (Folder 14)
      - Constitution, 1919 (Folder 15)
      - Economic Conditions. See also Germany, 1919-1933, Bavaria
        - General (Folder 16)
        - Agriculture (Folder 17)
        - Commerce (Folder 18)
        - Finance (Folder 19)
        - Industries (Folder 20)
        - Labor and Laboring Classes (Box 14.)
          - General (Folder 1)
          - Labor Court System (Folder 2)
          - Trade Unions (Folder 3)
          - Trade Unions -- Attitude to Unemployment (Folder 4)
          - Unemployed (Folder 5)
      - Education
        - General (Folder 6)
        - Elementary and Secondary (Folder 7)
        - Higher (Folder 8)
      - Election Campaigns, 1929-1932 (Folder 9)
      - Election Campaigns, 1929-1932 -- Nazi Methods (Folder 10)
      - Foreign Policy (Folder 11)
      - Public Welfare (Folder 12)
      - Public Welfare for the Unemployed (Folder 13)
      - Youth (Folder 14)
    - 1933-1945
      - General
        - Clippings (Folder 15)
        - Reports of Kurt R. Mattusch to American Consulate in Berlin
          - n.d. (Folder 16)
          - 1933 (Folder 17)
          - 1934 (Folder 18)
          - 1935 (Folder 19)
          - 1936 (Folder 20)
          - 1937 (Folder 21)
      - Agencies
        - Army (Folder 22)
        - Church (Folder 23)
        - Nazi Party (Folder 24)
        - Police
          - Criminal (Folder 25)
        - Secret (Box 15., Folder 1)
        - SA and SS (Folder 2)
      - Crime and Criminals (Folder 3)
      - Cultural Policy
        - General (Folder 4)
        - Architecture, Paintings, and Sculpture (Folder 5)
        - History (Folder 6)
        - Literature (Folder 7)
        - Music (Folder 8)
        - Philosophy (Folder 9)
      - Defenses (Folder 10)
      - Economic Conditions
        - General (Folder 11)
        - Agriculture (Folder 12)
        - Commerce
          - Domestic (Folder 13)
          - Foreign (Folder 14)
        - Finance (Folder 15)
        - Industries (Folder 16)
        - Industries, Mineral -- Conservation and Substitute Products (Folder 17)
        - Labor and Laboring Classes
          - General (Folder 18)
          - Trade Unions (Folder 19)
          - Unemployed (Folder 20)
          - Wages and Prices (Folder 21)
      - Education (Folder 22)
      - Election Campaign, 1936 (Folder 23)
      - Foreign Relations (Folder 24)
        - General
        - Czechoslovakia (Folder 25)
        - Great Britain (Folder 26)
        - Poland (Folder 27)
        - United States (Folder 28)
      - Gleichschaltung -- Consolidation of Power in Nazi Hands, 1933. See also Germany, 1933-1945, Economic Conditions, Labor and Laboring Classes (Folder 29)
      - Invalid, Disabled -- Procedure of Intern- ment in Concentration Camps (Folder 30)
      - Persecutions. See also Germany, 1933- 1945, Agencies and Gleichschaltung
        - General (Folder 31)
        - Jews (Folder 32)
        - Political Prisoners (Folder 33)
        - Rotary Clubs (Folder 34)
      - Population Policy (Folder 35)
      - Propaganda (Folder 36)
        - General
        - Anti-American (Folder 37)
        - Anti-Communist (Folder 38)
        - Anti-Nazi (Folder 39)
        - Pro-Nazi (Folder 40)
        - Pro-Nazi among Germans Living Abroad (Box 16., Folder 1)
      - Racial Question. See also Germany, 1933- 1945, Persecutions, Jews (Folder 2)
      - Refugees. See also Germany, 1933-1945, Persecutions, Jews (Folder 3)
      - Regions
        - Diepholz (Graftschaft) (Folder 4)
        - Mannheim, Baden (Folder 5)
        - Upper Silesia (Folder 6)
      - Rutha, Heinrich. Correspondence, 1934-1937 (Folder 7)
      - Scholz, Walter. Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Folder 8)
      - Serial Issuances (Folder 9)
      - "Die Todeskurve," short story, 1944. Typewritten copy (Folder 10)
      - Youth (Folder 11)
    - 1945-1956
      - General (Folder 12)
      - Agencies
        - Agencies of Allied Powers
          - General (Folder 13)
          - Allied Control Council (Folder 14)
          - Commander in Chief of French Forces in Germany (Folder 15)
          - United States Education Mission in Germany (Folder 16)
          - United States Office of Military Government for Germany
            - General (Folder 17)
            - Bizone (Folder 18)
            - Civil Administration of Germany (Box 17., Folder 1)
            - Economic Conditions (Folder 2)
            - Population (Folder 3)
            - Subagencies
              - General (Folder 4)
              - Civil Administration (Folder 5)
                - Division
                - Charts
                - Correspondence (Folder 6)
                - Maps (Folder 7)
                - Memoranda (Folder 8)
                - Proposals (Folder 9)
                - Reports (Folder 10)
                - Statement (Folder 11)
                - Economic Division. (Folder 12)
                - Office of German
                - Consultants
                - Field Offices
                - Coordinating Office (Folder 13)
                - Military Government for Hesse (Folder 14)
                - Office of Political Affairs (Folder 15)
                - Public Information Office (Folder 16)
                - Public Relations Service (Folder 17)
          - Territorial Organization of Germany (Folder 18)
        - Civil Administration of Germany
          - General (Folder 19)
          - Central (Folder 20)
          - Local (Folder 21)
      - Bizone (Box 18., Folder 1)
      - Bizone -- Inclusion of non-Governmental German Economic Organization of French Zone into Bizone (Folder 2)
      - Economic Conditions (Folder 3)
      - Impact of World War II
        - Hildesheim, town in Lower Saxony (Folder 4)
        - House of Frau Margarete Friedemann, Leipzig-- Cost of Restoration (Folder 5)
      - Political Parties (Folder 6)
      - Press -- United States Zone (Folder 7)
      - Prisoners of War (Folder 8)
      - Soviet Zone (Folder 9)
      - Territorial Issues (Folder 10)
      - Youth (Folder 11)
  - Housing and Building Materials (Folder 12)
  - India
    - General (Folder 13)
    - Art (Folder 14)
    - Gandhi, Mahatma (Folder 15)
    - Participation in World War II (Folder 16)
    - Phillips, William -- United States Ambassador (Folder 17)
    - Relationship with Great Britain (Folder 18)
  - Korea
    - Agencies
      - General (Folder 19)
      - Economic Research Center. Clippings; issuances; and a report, ed. by Kurt R. Mattusch, Industrial Structure of Korea, 2 vols. 1962-1963 with a preface by Kurt R. Mattusch "An Appraisal of Economic Policy," 1962 -- printed copy (Folder 20)
      - Processing Export Trade Association (Folder 21)
      - United States Operations Missions to Korea
        - Memoranda (Folder 22)
        - Reports
          - On Bank of Korea (Folder 23)
          - On Ministry of Commerce and Industry (Folder 24)
    - Economic Conditions (Box 19., Folder 1)
    - Mattusch, Kurt R., Korean Press on (Folder 2)
  - Labor Camps in Europe -- Historical Review (Folder 3)
  - Personalities
    - General (Folder 4)
    - Argentina (Folder 5)
    - Austria (Folder 6)
    - France (Folder 7)
    - Germany (Folder 8)
    - Great Britain (Folder 9)
    - United States (Folder 10)
  - Pribichevich, Stoyan, report on economic conditions of Southeast European countries and the USSR as potential suppliers of Germany, 1938? Typescript (Folder 11)
  - Underdeveloped Countries -- Effects of Accelerated Economic Development. Proposal for Panel Discussion, April 1957 (Folder 12)
  - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
    - General (Folder 13)
    - Foreign Economic Relations
      - General (Folder 14)
      - Germany, 1926-1939 (Folder 15)
    - Policy in East Europe (Folder 16)
    - Self-Sufficiency and Export Capacity. Report of United States government, 10 May 1939 (Folder 17)
    - Transportation Problems (Folder 18)
  - United States
    - General (Folder 19)
    - Chamberlain, John, "Books of the Times," series of articles, New York Times, 1942. Printed copies (Folder 20)
    - Economic Conditions (Folder 21)
    - Government
      - General (Folder 22)
      - Department of Agriculture (Folder 23)
      - Economic Cooperation Administration (Folder 24)
      - Foreign Economic Administration (Folder 25)
      - National Emergency Council (Box 20., Folder 1)
      - National Resources Committee (Folder 2-3)
      - Great Plains Committee (Folder 4)
      - National Resources Planning Board (Folder 5)
      - President's Committee on Administrative Management (Folder 6)
      - Tennessee Valley Authority (Folder 7)
      - Urbanism Committee (Folder 8)
      - Works Progress Administration (Box 21., Folder 1-2)
    - Lawyers and Law Business (Folder 3)
    - New York City (Folder 4)
    - Preparation for World War II (Folder 5)
    - Private Organizations
      - American Council on Public Affairs (Folder 6)
      - Council for Democracy (Folder 7)
      - National Planning Association (Folder 8)
    - Relationship with the USSR (Folder 9)
    - Youth -- Maryland (Folder 10)
  - World Economic Conditions
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Agriculture -- Asia (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Commerce
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Commodity Exchanges
        - Cocoa (Folder 3)
        - Coffee (Folder 4)
        - Copper (Folder 5)
        - Oil (Folder 6)
        - Rubber (Folder 7)
        - Sugar (Folder 8)
        - Tea (Folder 9)
        - Tobacco (Folder 10)
        - Wheat
          - General (Folder 11)
          - International Wheat Conference, London, August 1933 (Folder 12)
    - Finance (Folder 13)
    - Industry -- Automobile (Folder 14)
    - Transportation (Folder 15)
    - Unemployed (Folder 16)
  - World War, 1939-1945 -- Background (Folder 17)
- OVERSIZE FILE
  - United States Military Government in Germany. Charts, maps, summary of the fourth session of the Council of Foreign Ministers (France, Great Britain, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, United States) Moscow, 1947 (Box 23.)
- AUDIO-VISUAL
  - See Photograph Card Catalog (Box 10. A-V)
- INCREMENT
  - January 1984 (Box 22 & 24.)